A Guide to the Clark Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10734
Clark Family Papers 1804-1964
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10734
ca. 1,200 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase 1987 November 17
Scope and Content
This collection, 1804-1964, ca. 1200 items, contains correspondence, personal papers, and business and legal papers of the Pleasant Clark family and William Lawson family, as well as of their descendants in the Asher family and Elder family. Living in the Virginia areas of Hat Creek and Lynchburg, and in Campbell County, Charlotte County, and Halifax County, these families apparently served as prominent plantation owners, businessmen, and local elected officials.
Business papers include tobacco receipts from 1854-1934 and tax receipts from 1834-1913 which attest to their holdings during this period. Accounts and receipts, 1804-1933, have recorded the daily plantation activities of the Pleasant Clark family, and the transactions of William Lawson's business, each with numerous references to local residents. The hire and sale of slaves, ca. 1827-1861, has been recorded chiefly in promissory notes, and, to a lesser extent, receipts, tax receipts, and legal documents. Other legal documents establish family kinship, and include deed transfers, declarations of bankruptcy, and insurance papers.
The bulk of the correspondence is personal, with some from each family. In the Asher family, the early religious work done by Louis C. Asher is described in letters to his wife, Alberta Elder Asher. Letters from friends and family to Alberta Asher usually pertain to her health, and to that of various relatives. Cassie O. Clark received most of the Clark family's letters. Early letters from John P. Clark to his siblings include interesting notes on his life in St. Louis, Missouri., Alberta Asher's brother, wrote letters primarily concerned with his efforts to find employment, and his personal relationship with Dollie Henderson. William A. Lawson received several letters from his brother, Robert Lawson, who told of his business travels. Correspondence of the Lawson family, as well as business and miscellaneous letters complete the series.
Container List
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence of Alberta Elder Asher, 1896-1935, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence--Alberta Elder Asher from Louis C. Asher, 1893-1910, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence--Alberta Elder Asher from Bertha Elder, 1896-1907 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence--Alberta Elder Asher from Evelyn Hill, 1898-1900 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence--Alberta Elder Asher from [Rose] Elder, 1900-1910, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence--Alberta Elder Asher from Mattie Womack, 1908-1910, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence--Alberta Elder Asher from Julia and Marian Asher, 1910-1935 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Julia and Marian Asher, 1911-1926, 1978-1980 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Louis C. Asher, 1878-1901, 1928-1930, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Cassie O. Clark, 1906, 1924-1928, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Cassie O. Clark (Christmas Cards), 1912, 1926-1927, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence of the Clark family, (1849-1899)1927, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence of William Andrew Elder, 1890-1901, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence--William Andrew Elder from Dollie Henderson, 1897-1901, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence--William Andrew Elder from Hiram and Rose Elder, 1901 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence--Dollie Henderson from William Andrew Elder, 1898-1901 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence--William A. Lawson from Robert Lawson, 1826-1840 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence of William A. Lawson, 1835-1853 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence of the Lawson family, 1885-1901, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence--Miscellaneous, 1857-1901, n.d. (Box Box 2)
- Business and Legal Papers
  - Business Papers--Accounts, 1825-1903, n.d.; (3 folders) (Box Box 2)
  - Business Papers--Correspondence, 1829-1926, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  - Business Papers--Promissory Notes, 1812-1918, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  - Business Papers--Receipts, 1800-1879; (4 folders) (Box Box 3)
  - Business Papers--Receipts, 1880-1933, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 4)
  - Business Papers--Tax Receipts, 1834-1913 (Box Box 4)
  - Business Papers--Tobacco Receipts and Correspondence re Tobacco, 1854-1934 (Box Box 4)
  - Legal Papers, 1820-1905 (Box Box 4)
- Miscellaneous
  - Genealogy Research, 1964, n.d. (Box Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1861-1933, n.d. (Box Box 4)
  - Poetry, n.d. (Box Box 4)